Register of the World War I pictorial collection
Hoover Institution Archives
World War I pictorial collection
1914-1920
XX247
Hoover Institution Archives
126 envelopes, 15 album boxes, 19 manuscript boxes, 14 card file boxes, 8 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder, 1 painting (40.7 linear feet)
Photographs, cartoons, and postcards depicting a variety of scenes and personalities from World War I.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Photographs, cartoons, and postcards depicting a variety of scenes and personalities from World War I.
World War, 1914-1918--Pictorial works.; Slides (Photography).
- 9 hand-tinted glass plates depicting activities of the Italian navy during World War I (Boxes 1, 34-35)
- 304 slides with viewer depicting war scenes in France during World War I (Box 2)
- Glass slides depicting war scenes in France during World War I (Box 3)
- Glass slides of war scenes in France (Box 4)
- Album of photographs of the headquarters of the Austro-Hungarian Armeeoberkommando, Baden, Austria, 1917; album of photographs of the Austrian VI Korpskommando, Krakow, Poland, 1914; album of postcards of the A.E.F. University, Beaune, France; 2 albums of postcards of German troops on the Eastern Front (Box 5)
- 3 albums of postcards of German troops on the Western Front; 1 album of postcards of German naval and aerial forces (Box 6)
- Album of postcards of Kaiser Wilhelm II, General Paul von Hindenburg, and other German war leaders; 3 albums of German patriotic postcards, principally drawings and caricatures (Box 7)
- 5 card file boxes of postcards of German troops and patriotic German caricatures and drawings (Boxes 8-12)
- Card file box of German postcards, including a number of International Red Cross postcards of prisoners of war in several countries (Box 13)
- 6 card file boxes of postcards of Russian troops and patriotic Russian caricatures and drawings (Boxes 14-19)
- 3 boxes of stereograph images (Box 20)
  Scope and Contents note
  1 print of British submarines at anchor in the Thames; 1 print of German sailors in the Mediterranean; 12 various prints of French cavalry, infantry, and artillery, 1914-1915; 1 print of German machine gun unit, 1914; 13 prints of war damage in France and Belgium, showing destroyed buildings, towns, and refugees; 17 prints of British, Canadian, South African, and Australian troops in Belgium and France, 1914, showing columns, training and fighting; 20 prints of U.S. Army troops undergoing basic training at Plattsburg, New York; 2 miscellaneous prints from the Philippine Islands; 3 prints of Russian troops on the Eastern Front; 1 print of Marshal Joseph Joffre at Columbia University; 6 prints of Belgian and French troops in battle, 1914; 1 print of Field Marshal Earl French addressing troops; 2 prints of British Army camp life at the front; 9 prints of Italian troops engaged on the Alpine front; 1 print of civilians aboard the USS Connecticut; 1 print of Queen Marie of Romania with Prime Minister Y. C. C Bratann, 10 May 1915; 1 print of King Ferdinand of Romania with Prime Minister Y. C. C. Bratann, 10 May 1915; 10 various photographs of French regular and colonial troops engaged in fighting on the Western Front; 2 prints of British recruits entraining for the Western Front; 3 prints depicting the effects of Zeppelin raids on Britain; 7 prints of British troops engaged in fighting on the Western Front, employing bicycles and armoured vehicles; 8 prints of German field fortifications in France, showing arrangement of barbed wire, artillery, and trenches, 1914; 10 various prints showing battlefields after fighting with the collection of dead, prisoners, grave sites, and wounded; 1 print of the landing at Gallipoli, 1915.
- 2 boxes of stereograph images (Box 21)
  5 prints of the Gallipoli campaign with troop transports, Allied troops, and Turkish coastal artillery batteries; 3 various prints of Italian troops; 2 prints of the interior of a British munitions factory; 1 print of Woodrow Wilson; 1 print of David Lloyd-George; 25 various prints depicting French troops of the Western Front, 1914-1915; 5 prints of war booty collected in Great Britain for fund raising purposes, including weapons from the SMS Emden, aircraft and field artillery; 5 prints of Russian troops on the Eastern Front showing trenches, and heavy siege artillery; 9 miscellaneous scenes from the European War, depicting aerial warfare, colonial troops, and war damage; 1 print of Sarajevo, Bosnia; 1 print of Belgian troops defending a canal in Flanders, 1914; 4 prints of field kitchens of the various warring powers; 3 various photographs of war refugees; 4 prints of Italian troops fighting in Alpine areas; 6 prints of U.S. Army of Occupation troops in Koblenz, Germany; 14 various prints of French troops engaged on the Western Front, including dragoons, colonial troops, and infantry; 9 prints of the peace conference at Versailles; 1 print of President Raymond Poincaré during a visit to the front together with several officers; 1 print of the assembled royalty at Queen Alexandra of Russia's coronation, Moscow, 1896; 4 various prints of Russian infantry, Uhlans, and other mounted units; 2 prints of battleships -- one British, one Austro-Hungarian; 4 prints of various weapons, including primitive anti-aircraft artillery, field telescopes, and aircraft; 6 prints of victorious Allied troops on parade in Paris; 1 print of Czech soldiers marching on Wencelaus Sqaure; 7 prints of the area around Chateau-Thierry; 17 prints of U.S. Army troops training in France at target practice with small arms, anti-aircraft machine guns, and other activities; 2 prints of General J. J. Pershing in France, and Washington D.C.; 7 prints of victorious U.S. troops in London, and New York; 6 glass slides of U.S. posters
- Cartoons, relating to World War I, mostly from French newspapers, as well as from German, Italian, Dutch, Belgian, Norwegian, Spanish, and Swiss newspapers, 1914-1918 (Boxes 22-26)
- Political postcards from various countries (Boxes 27-30)
- German maps of Austria/Italy (Map case)
- 22 glass plates depicting the German Army during World War I (Box 31)
- Glass slides depicting activities of the French Army in France during World War I (Box 32)
- Postcards depicting Russian propaganda, 1914-1918 (Box 33)
- Oversize prints and lithographs depicting miscellaneous aspects of World War I, especially the Isonzo front (Box 36)
- Not yet described (Boxes 37-38)
- Postcards depicting scenes from World War I, including flags and national emblems of belligerents, religious scenes, and drawings by Louis Raemekers (Envelope mA, B-C)
- Photographs from World War I, depicting airplanes, aviators, aerial views of military positions, dirigibles, tanks, artillery war damage, battleships, infantry, training camps, civilian population and significant individuals, among them Kaiser Wilhelm II, the German Crown Prince, Paul von Hindenburg, Erich von Ludendorff, John J. Pershing, Victor Emmanuel III, Georges Clemenceau, and Peter I of Serbia (Envelope mD, E-L)
- 28 photographs of Quaker relief work in France during World War I (Envelope M)
  Also includes scenes of battlefields and war damage.
- 16 photographs depicting activities of the French army in France during World War I (Envelope N)
- 18 oversize photographs depicting activities of the A.E.F in France during World War I (Envelope m*O (map case))
- Stereo photos of Belgian, Turkish, British, and French soldiers, and of scenes of battle damage on the Western front, during World War I (Envelope P-Q)
- Album (fR) of scenes in France during World War I (Box 39)
- 2 photographs of a U.S. sailor and a British pilot during World War I (Envelope S)
- 45 photographs, taken from the air, of the war front in France, 1918 (Envelope T)
- Album (fU) of photographs depicting war damage in France and Belgium during World War I, together with scenes of the results of post-war reconstruction (Box 40)
- 66 photographs depicting activities of the A.E.F. in France during World War I, including photographs of General John J. Pershing (Envelope V)
- Album of photographs depicting activities of the A.E.F in France (Album fW)
- Photographs mainly depicting activities of the A.E.F. in France (Envelope mX)
- Photographs mainly depicting activities of the A.E.F. in France (Envelope Y-Z)
- Photographs of war scenes in France and Algeria, 1918-1919 (Envelope AA)
- Photographs of war scenes in France and of unidentified aerial scenes (Envelope AB)
- 3 prints of French soldiers interned in Switzerland (Envelope AC)
- Photographs and postcards of Italian soldiers and scenes on the Italo-Austrian front (Envelope AD)
- Postcards and pictorial booklets of war damage in Louvain, Ypres, Dixmude and other Belgian cities (Envelope AE)
- Photographs and postcards of French soldiers' scenes on the Western Front and war damage in France (Envelope AF)
- Drawings and postcard caricatures of French soldiers and conditions in France during World War I (Envelope AG)
- Pictorial booklets of war damage in France and scenes on the Western Front (Envelope AH-AI)
- Photographs of German troops in Poland and of scenes on the Polish front (Envelope AJ)
- Photographs of German troops in France and scenes on the Western Front (Envelope AK)
- Photographs of German and Bulgarian troops in the Balkans, principally in Serbia (Envelope AL)
- Photographs of German troops on the Russian front (Envelope AM)
- Photographs of Austrian and Italian troops on the Italo-Austrian front (Envelope AN)
- 6 prints of Allied soldiers in German prison camps (Envelope AO)
- German aerial photographs of sections of the Western Front (Envelope AP)
- Pictorial booklets of German troops on the Eastern and Western Fronts (Envelope AQ)
- Postcards of members of royal families of the Central Powers (Envelope AR)
- Postcards depicting German airplanes and scenes of aerial warfare (Envelope AS)
- Postcards of German troops and war scenes on the Eastern and Western Fronts (Envelope AT)
- Postcard caricatures and drawings of German soldiers and conditions in Germany during World War I (Envelope AU)
- Postcard drawings and caricatures of Austrian soldiers (Envelope AV)
- Photographs of British and other Allied war leaders (Envelope AW)
- Photographs of the visits of King George V and Queen Mary of Great Britain to the Western Front and to the Clyde shipyards in Scotland (Envelope AX)
- Photographs of British seamen and ships (Envelope AY)
- 6 prints of British troops in the Middle East (Envelope AZ)
- Photographs of British troops and war scenes on the Western Front (Envelope BA-BB)
- American aerial photographs of German lines in France, 1918 (Envelope BC-BL)
- Photographs of American soldiers on the Western Front, including 3 prints of American soldiers captured by Germans (Envelope BM)
- Photographs of American patriotic posters (Envelope BN)
- Photograph of General Paul von Hindenburg (Envelope BO)
- 10 panoramic views of sections of the Western Front, constructed from composite photographs (Envelope BP)
- 15 prints of the funeral of Colonel Johann Chadzopulos, commander of the 4th Greek Army Corps (Envelope BQ)
- Photographs of American soldiers in France (Envelope mBR-mBS)
- Panoramic aerial view of the Moselle River, constructed from composite photographs (Envelope m*BT (map case))
- Reproductions of four paintings by Guy Arnoux entitled "Quatre Canons Français," depicting the evolution of French artillery from the Middle Ages to World War I (Envelope mBU)
- 1 print of the Finnish General Karl Mannerheim with the German General Ruediger von der Goltz, 1917 (Envelope BV)
- Prints of disabled French soldiers undergoing vocational rehabilitation training (Envelope BW-BX)
- Printed drawings of German troops, uniforms, and scenes in German colonies (Envelope BY)
- 23 photographs of scenes in Germany, prisoners and prison camps during World War I (Envelope mBZ)
- 49 aerial photographs, 1918 (Envelope CA)
- 55 prints of scenes of World War I, including bombardment, troops, tanks, aerial photographs, etc.; 1 souvenir album of postcards, "Les Americains en France" (Envelope CB)
- 1 print of Paris Caucus (American soldiers); 2 miscellaneous pictorial pages (1 leaflet requesting aid for French forces, 1 humorous leaflet entitled "The Kaiser's Despair") (Envelope CC)
- 2 prints of Salvation Army women feeding U.S. troops in France; 4 prints of front line U.S. troops with radio equipment, and at work in field post; 1 print of Major General Edward M. Lewis, U.S. Army; 1 print of unidentified Italian officer; 1 print of various foreign orders and decorations won by U.S. troops; 10 prints of front line and rear areas with U.S. armoured vehicles, and motor transport; 1 print of 13 U.S. Army soldiers of 12 nationalities; 4 prints of Allied troops at Vladivostock, Russia; 2 prints of U.S. Navy officers in Washington D.C.; 3 prints of Italian troops on the Brenta front, northern Italy (Album fCD-fCE, Box 41)
- 8 various prints of camp life in the front line and rear areas defended by the U.S. Army, in France; 2 prints of General J. J. Pershing inspecting units of the 1st Division in France; 10 prints of U.S. Army troops on the Western Front while employed in field post, bridge and road construction, and other service activities; 9 prints of U.S. troops in battle in the St. Mihiel and Argonne sectors; 1 print of Secretary of War Newton D. Baker as he visits wounded in hospital (Album fCG-fCI)
- 6 various photographs of U.S. troops fighting in France; 1 photograph of Major General George W. Read; 1 print of Archangel, Russia from the air; 1 print of Lieutenant General Robert W. Bullard; 7 prints of U.S. troops engaged in fighting, France, 1917; 3 prints of U.S. troops in camp, France, 1917-1818; 3 prints of U.S. troops together with French peasants; 1 photograph of U.S. troops repairing a damaged bridge; 3 prints of U.S. troops engaged in repair of roads (Album fCJ-fCL)
- 6 panoramic prints of U.S. troops, cemeteries and battle sites in France, 1919 (Envelope m*CM (map case))
- 1 print of 25,000 American soldiers in formation in the shape of the Liberty Bell, Camp Dix, N. J., 1918; 22 prints of an unidentified American mission visiting France during World War I (Envelope mCN)
- 4 drawings on the backs of menus from a Paris restaurant, celebrating the end of the war, 1918 (Envelope mCO)
- 7 prints of British soldiers and pilots in France during World War I (Envelope CP)
- 27 prints of Woodrow Wilson and the U.S. delegation to the Paris Peace Conference, 1919 (Envelope mCQ)
- 430 prints depicting activities of the Austro-Hungarian army on the Eastern Front, 1917-1919 (Envelope CR-CW)
- 2 prints of King Albert I of Belgium, one taken in 1914, and the other depicting him with his consort, Queen Elisabeth, in a parade in Brussels, marking the end of World War I, 1918 (Envelope mCX)
- 1 print depicting the destruction of a building during World War I, from The National Magazine, p. 205 (caption: "After the Bombardment"), 1914 November (Envelope CY)
- 61 prints depicting military activities during World War I in France, including prints of Georges Clemenceau, General Pershing, and Field Marshal Foch (Envelope CZ)
- 15 prints depicting German soldiers (one with Belgian prisoners) in France and Belgium (Envelope DA)
  Includes one of Count Ferdinand von Zeppelin.
- 6 prints depicting German soldiers with war equipment, supplies, etc., and German women working in Berlin, and battlefields (Envelope DB)
- 18 prints depicting German and Russian soldiers in Poland, including one print depicting Austrian soldiers on their way to the Italian front (Envelope DC)
- 1 print depicting Crown Prince Wilhlem reviewing troops, circa 1914 (Envelope DD)
- 27 prints depicting British Army and Calvary units on parade, circa 1915 (Envelope DE)
- 49 prints and 47 postcards depicting conditions, war damage and military forces in Italy, 1917-1919 (Envelope DF)
- 4 prints of the Russian Military Cemetery at Mourmelon le Grand, France (Envelope DG)
- 1 postcard of the 316th supply train of the A.E.F., at Nogent, France, 1918 (Envelope DH)
- 1 photograph album of the American Expeditionary Forces (Album fDI)
- 1 print of a painting by G. L. Jaulmes, entitled "Le Départ des Américains pour la Guerre" (the departure of the Americans for war) (Envelope DJ)
- 6 negatives of posters issued by the U.S. (Envelope DK)
- Photographs of posters (20 albums in 9 boxes) issued by the U.S. and a number of other countries, relating to the war effort during World War I, 1914-1919 (Album fDL-fDT)
- 3 prints depicting unidentified award ceremonies (Envelope DU)
- 12 prints depicting aerial views of France taken by German pilots for reconnaissance, 1918; printed map of Iran, 1918, in German; 12 panoramic prints of French countryside taken by German pilots for reconnaissance, undated (Envelope mDV)
- 29 prints, on five pages from a scrapbook, depicting aerial views of France, maps and scenes of war, 1916-1918 (Envelope mDW)
- 11 prints depicting trenches and military camps on the Western Front, as well as cities such as Verdun, Sedan and Coblenz (Envelope m*DX (map case))
- Photo album depicting prints of Austro-Hungarian troops, automobiles, and armament during World War I (Envelope DY)
  Includes 1 print of Archduke Franz Salvator, representative of Francis Joseph.
- 1 print depicting a class of young boys and girls from the Belgian town of Uladsloo holding up a placard expressing their gratitude to the Commission for Relief in Belgium, 1918 (Envelope DZ)
- Album of postcards describing the German war effort and depicting German troops in Galicia and on the Western Front, naval battle scenes, and cities and towns in France, Poland, Germany, and Belgium (some destroyed), 1914-1916 (Album fEA)
- 21 postcards depicting members of the German imperial family at the time of World War I (Envelope EB)
- 22 postcards and prints depicting Woodrow Wilson, Georges Clemenceau, Kaiser Wilhelm II, Crown Prince Wilhem, General Paul von Hindenburg and other German military leaders; German soldiers (dead and alive) and prisoners, captured German artillery and tank displayed on the Place de la Concorde in Paris, a German observation balloon, the American cemetery of Belleau Wood and other grave sites, and unidentified barracks and submarine, 1914-1919 (Envelope EC)
- 1 print depicting both sides of a medal commemorating Count Ferdinand von Zeppelin and a German aerial attack over London, 1915 August 17-18 (Envelope ED)
- 1 print depicting C. B. Kelland in uniform, undated (Envelope EE)
- 3 prints depicting the U.S.A.T Mount Vernon transporting German prisoners of war from Vladivostok (Envelope EF)
- 1 print of Kaiser Wilhelm II with Marshals Paul von Hindenburg and Erich Ludendorfff; and 1 tin type of Field Marshal Sir John French (Envelope EG)
- 40 postcard portraits of various American, British and other Allied military leaders (Envelope EH)
- 63 postcards of assorted World War I scenes (Envelope EI)
- 48 prints depicting the U.S.A.T Logan transporting Czechoslovak prisoners of war from Vladivostok, 1920 (Envelope mEJ)
- 1 sketch of General Erich von Falkenhayn German Chief of Staff, by O. Henspel, 1917 (Envelope EK)
- 3 postcards including depictions of Marshals Ferdinand Foch and Joseph Joffre (Envelope EL)
- 10 prints of tanks in World War I (Envelope EM)